Guide to the Henrietta C. Bartlett Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1905-1960, n.d.; Series I; 2.1' (5 boxes)
  - LETTERS TO HENRIETTA C. BARTLETT
    - Trinity College, Dublin, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 245)
      Thank-you certificate signed by J. Gilbart Smyly for the donation of a copy of Catalog of Early English Books
    - Troxell, Gilbert McCoy
      See: Elizabethan Club, Box 1, folder 64
    - Trustees and Guardians of Shakespeare's Birthplace, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 246)
      Includes: Letters from Levi Fox
    - Tyler, Philippa, 1940 Jan 1 (Box 5, Folder 247)
    - Unger, Emma
      See: Series III, Research Files, "Clippings of the Britwell Library and Quaritch books in New York," Box 14, folder 389
    - University of Bristol, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 248)
    - University of Edinburgh Library, 1923-35 (Box 5, Folder 249)
    - University of Illinois at Urbana- Champaign, Library, 1946-54 (Box 5, Folder 250)
    - University of Kentucky Libraries, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 251)
      Includes: Letters from Lawrence Sidney Thompson
    - University of London, School of Librarianship, 1926 May 31 (Box 5, Folder 252)
    - Valentine, P. A., 1946 Feb 25 (Box 5, Folder 253)
    - Vickery, Willis, 1918, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 254)
    - Walker, Emery, 1929 July 16 (Box 5, Folder 255)
    - Walters Art Gallery, Baltimore, 1950 Mar 17 (Box 5, Folder 256)
      Includes: TL from Dorothy Eugenia Miner
    - Ward, Adolphus William, [1920?] Jun 18 (Box 5, Folder 257)
    - Weld, John, 1936 Dec 24 (Box 5, Folder 258)
    - Wells, Gabriel, 1923-41 (Box 5, Folder 259)
      Includes: Copy of a letter by HCB
    - Wetsell, Harris P., 1937 May 14 (Box 5, Folder 260)
    - White, Newport B.
      See: Marsh's Library, Box 3, folder 157
    - White, William Augustus, 1921-23 (Box 5, Folder 261)
    - Wickser, Philip J., 1947-48 (Box 5, Folder 262)
    - William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, 1934 Apr 7 (Box 5, Folder 263)
      Includes: ALS from Cora Edgerton Sanders
    - Wilmerding, Lucius
    - Wilson, John Dover, 1929-48 (Box 5, Folder 264-265)
    - Wing, Donald Goddard, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 266)
      See also: Yale University Library, Box 5, folders 273-278
    - Winship, George Parker, 1915-25 (Box 5, Folder 267)
    - Witherspoon, Alexander M., 1925, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 268)
    - Withinsen, O. F., 1920 Jul 20 (Box 5, Folder 269)
    - Wyatt, Barbara P., 1940-41 (Box 5, Folder 270-271)
    - Wyatt, Tema, 1939-41 (Box 5, Folder 272)
      Includes: Group photograph with first names listed on back
    - Yale University Library, 1927-59 (Box 5, Folder 273-278)
      Includes: Lists of material given to the library by HCB, and acknowledgment letters signed by library officials
      Includes: Carbon of letter dated April 29, 1927 from HCB to Andrew Keogh regarding the gift of her papers, and an earlier letter from Charles G. Bartlett about the gift
      Includes: Letters from James Babb, Andrew Keogh, Bernhard Knollenberg, Charles E. Rush, Chauncey Brewster Tinker, and Donald Wing
    - Yale University Press, 1939-40 (Box 5, Folder 279)
      Includes: Letters from Norman Vaux Donaldson
    - Yale University School of Fine Arts, Gallery of Fine Arts, 1934 May 1 (Box 5, Folder 280)
    - Yorke, Angela, [1941?] Jul 15 (Box 5, Folder 281)
    - Yorke, Gerald, 1939-41 (Box 5, Folder 282)
    - Young, Owen D., 1932 Feb 24 (Box 5, Folder 283)
    - Zentralbibliothek Zürich, 1946 Jun 3 (Box 5, Folder 284)
    - ----, Marjorie, 1940-41 (Box 5, Folder 285)
    - Unidentified, 1934-46, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 286)
      Includes: Typescript draft of letter from HCB to an unidentified recipient
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cock, Morris F. to Alfred W. Pollard, 1914 Jul 9 (Box 5, Folder 287)
    - Cushing, Harvey to Belle da Costa Greene, 1930 Dec 26 (Box 5, Folder 288)
    - Greg, W. W. (Walter Wilson) to "Dear Sir," [Anne Stokely Pratt, Yale University Reference Librarian] and copies of her replies, 1947-48 (Box 5, Folder 289)
    - Hack, Emily E. L. to Dr. Williamson, [n.y.] May 10 (Box 5, Folder 290)
    - Holford, George Lindsay to Mr. Murray, 1920 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 291)
    - Jaggard, William to Alfred W. Pollard, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 292)
    - Newdigate, Bernard H. to Alfred W. Pollard, 1914 Feb 16 (Box 5, Folder 293)
    - Stevens, Henry to Messrs. Austin Baldwin & Co., Bankers, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 294)
      Copy of TL dated Feb. 10, 1873 concerning the arrival in America of George Brinley's copy of the Gutenberg Bible
    - Thomas, C. Edgar to Alfred W. Pollard, 1921 Jun 2 (Box 5, Folder 295)
    - White, William Augustus. Copy of TL to Luther Samuel Livingston, 1912 Jan 27 (Box 5, Folder 296)
      Includes: Typescript page entitled "Data about works of Thomas Nash in the collection of Mr. W. A. White of Brooklyn, N.Y."
- Writings, 1471-1935, n.d.; Series II; 3.3' (8 boxes)
  - WRITINGS FOR PUBLICATION
    - Census of Shakespeare's Quartos, Introduction and chapter on Hamlet, ca. 1916 (Box 6, Folder 297)
    - "Extant Autograph Material by Shakespeare's Fellow Dramatists," Typescript article with corrections, and proofs, ca. 1929 (Box 6, Folder 298)
    - "First editions of Shakespeare's Quartos", 1935 (Box 6, Folder 299)
      Included in: Transactions of the Bibliographical Society, Vol. XVI, No. 2. Sept. 1935
  - LECTURES
    - Textual Materials
      - Full Texts
        - Elizabethan Club Lecture, April 30, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 300)
        - Yale Lectures. Bibliography I and II, and the Yale University Library, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 301)
        - "Alexander Pope," typescript lecture with manuscript corrections (Box 6, Folder 302)
        - "Bibliographical Research as an Aid to Editing English Texts," typescript lecture with manuscript corrections, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 303)
        - "Herrick and the Cavalier Poets," typescript lecture with manuscript corrections (Box 6, Folder 304)
        - "Shakespeare's Texts," Edwin Forrest Memorial Lecture, Philadelphia, April 22, 1927, typescript lecture with manuscript corrections (Box 6, Folder 305)
      - Notes
        - Cataloguing Lectures: Incunabula, ca. 1928 (Box 6, Folder 306-307)
        - Cataloguing Lectures: Early English, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 308-309)
          Includes: Sample pages of an early book
        - Cataloguing Lectures: Modern English and American, ca. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 310-311)
        - Cataloguing Lectures: Samples, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 312)
          Consists of copies of notes from various lectures
        - Rare Books and Collectors. "Series A", ca. 1922 (Box 6, Folder 313-314)
        - Collectors and Collecting. "Series B", ca. 1929-32 (Box 6, Folder 315-317)
        - Manuscripts. Including notes on Lindisfarne Gospels. "Series C", ca. 1936 (Box 6, Folder 318-320)
        - Invention of Printing. "Series D", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 321-323)
        - Shakespeare Lectures. Forerunners of Shakespeare. "Series E", ca. 1930 (Box 7, Folder 324-326)
        - Shakespeare Lectures. "Series F", ca. 1931 (Box 7, Folder 327-328)
        - Shakespeare Lectures. "Series G", ca. 1933 (Box 7, Folder 329-331)
        - Miscellaneous Lectures, including English Book-Building, English Prose Fiction. "Series H", ca. 1924-30 (Box 7, Folder 332-334)
        - Material used in teaching the history of printing, 1471-1675, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 335-340)
          Includes: various original and facsimile leaves from books and manuscripts, and a watercolor chart illuatrating the history of the English language
      - Glass Slides
        - Series A-D, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 341)
        - Series E-F; slides and negatives not in series (Box 9, Folder 342)
        - Portraits, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 343)
        - Early Books; Royalty; "Views" (interior and exterior, images of books and art) (Box 11, Folder 344)
        - Title pages, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 345)
- Research Files, 1900-1948, n.d.; Series III; 1.25' (3 boxes)
  - AUTHORS
    - William Blake, 1925, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 346)
    - John Bunyan, 1921, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 347)
    - Lewis Carroll, 1928, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 348)
    - William Caxton, 1924, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 349)
    - Geoffrey Chaucer, 1925-31, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 350)
    - Daniel Defoe, 1906-29, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 351)
    - Michael Drayton, 1931, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 352)
    - Robert Greene, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 353)
    - Thomas Heywood, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 354)
    - Ben Jonson, 1925-32, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 355)
    - Thomas Malory, 1930-34, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 356)
    - Christopher Marlowe, 1921-25, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 357)
    - Thomas Middleton, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 358)
    - Thomas More, 1930-31, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 359)
    - George Peele, 1934, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 360)
    - Alexander Pope, 1923-34 (Box 13, Folder 361)
    - William Shakespeare, ca. 1920-35 (Box 13, Folder 362-367)
    - Notes on Shakespeare editions, 1946-47, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 368-369)
      Includes: Letters from A. N. L. Munby regarding Geoffrey Keynes
      Includes: TLS from Matthew Wilson Black
    - Shakespeare: Notes on copies of spurious plays of Shakespeare, 1920 Aug (Box 13, Folder 370)
      Copied by secretary to S. de Ricci for Miss Bartlett, Paris
    - Philip Sidney, 1928-31, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 371)
    - Edmund Spencer, 1930-34, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 372)
  - SUBJECTS
    - The Bible, 1928-36, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 373)
    - Collectors and Provenance, 1920-29, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 374-375)
    - Early Education of Women, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 376)
    - Notebook with manuscript notes entitled "Education of Women Exhibition in Honor of 25th Anniversary of Barnard College", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 377)
      "Books belonged chiefly to G. A. Plimpton; Exhibition arranged by H. C. Bartlett"
    - Elizabethan Writing, 1924-33, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 378)
    - Paper and Bindings, 1926-28, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 379)
    - Printers and Printing, 1929-33, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 380-381)
    - Specimen pages from various printers, 1922-37, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 382)
    - Theatre, Plays, Players, 1922-30, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 383)
  - LIBRARIES AND COLLECTIONS
    - Henry E. Huntington Library, 1914-23, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 384)
    - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1912-34, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 385)
    - Bound volume of notes and lists on the library of William Augustus White (Box 14, Folder 386)
      Includes: Pages from Hand-List of Early English Books, Mostly of the Elizabethan Period, Collected by W. A. White, "Digested from Card Catalogue made by Miss Henrietta C. Bartlett," 1914
    - "Corrections, and Additional Notes, to Miss Henrietta C. Bartlett's Catalog of the Library of W. A. White," typescript and manuscript notes (Box 14, Folder 387)
    - "List of books from the Quaritch and Britwell sales," bound volume of typescript lists, 1920, 1924 (Box 14, Folder 388)
    - "Clippings of the Britwell Library and Quaritch books in New York," bound volume, 1911-25 (Box 14, Folder 389)
      Includes: ANS from Emma Unger
    - Beverly Chew, "Notice of Probate to Beneficiaries," regarding her will, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 390)
    - Miscellaneous Libraries, 1923-30, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 391-392)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1928-34, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 393-395)
  - OTHER FILES
    - Notebook, including notes on the description of rare books, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 396)
    - Miscellaneous sales catalogs, 1921-26, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 397)
    - Miscellaneous printed items, 1900-19, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 398)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1929-48, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 399-404)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1906-36, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 405-414)
    - Paperweight[?], fabric-covered wood with silver-colored metalwork, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 415)
- Hroswitha Club, 1940-1961, n.d.; Series IV; 0.2' (1 box)
  - Club Minutes, 1944-61 (Box 16, Folder 416-418)
  - Club Membership, ca. 1952-1961 (Box 16, Folder 419)
  - Lists of books presented to the Club, 1950-52 (Box 16, Folder 420)
  - "Astronomical and Scientific Books," typescript lecture, [1961] (Box 16, Folder 421)
    "Talk Given at the Hroswitha Club Meeting of January 19, 1961 by Mrs. Hugh Bullock"
  - Copies of Club by-laws, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 422)
  - Printed material collected by or published for the Club, ca. 1940-61 (Box 16, Folder 423)
    Includes: TLS from Thomas R. Adams, Chapin Library, Williams College, dated May 23, 1956
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.2' (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 7, folder 303 (Box 17, Folder 424)
  - Box 13, folder 347 (Box 17, Folder 425)
  - Box 13, folder 348 (Box 17, Folder 426)
  - Box 13, folder 350 (Box 17, Folder 427)
  - Box 13, folder 351 (Box 17, Folder 428)
  - Box 13, folder 356 (Box 17, Folder 429)
  - Box 13, folder 367 (Box 17, Folder 430)
  - Box 13, folder 374 (Box 17, Folder 431)
  - Box 13, folder 375 (Box 17, Folder 432)
  - Box 14, folder 378 (Box 17, Folder 433)
  - Box 14, folder 379 (Box 17, Folder 434)
  - Box 14, folder 380 (Box 17, Folder 435)
  - Box 14, folder 383 (Box 17, Folder 436)
  - Box 14, folder 384 (Box 17, Folder 437)
  - Box 14, folder 385 (Box 17, Folder 438)
  - Box 14, folder 391 (Box 17, Folder 439)
  - Box 14, folder 393 (Box 17, Folder 440)
  - Box 15, folders 412-414 (Box 17, Folder 441-442)
- Oversize, 1.0' (1 portfolio)
  Oversize contains materials from II, arranged in the order in which they appear in the series
  - Cataloguing Lectures: Incunabula (from Series II), ca. 1928 (Box PORT, Folder 443)
  - Material used in teaching the history of printing (from Series II) (Box PORT, Folder 444-445)